good morning friends can you hear me please can we make a technical check
if you are able to hear me please write to the chat box okay okay thank you for feedback
now let me share my document this week the document of this week let me
upload my documents but first of all yes so unfortunately i forget my mouse in somewhere
so i'm trying to use my pad of the laptop so i don't like using pad so it will be some time
to make some arrangements using pad is not easy for me in practice
this model i think it is okay okay friends welcome to my course this week is the third
week i think as i remember we will continue at the last point i think
i think we finished the last ppt document so this is the new topic the name of the topic is the
from intuition to rigor let me continue from that point okay
in software engineering we start from a very messy situation
in the real world we observe structured data behaviors and events yes bugs happen users complain
systems slow down and teams react based on experience or intuition at the stage
information exists but it is not organized and it's hard to reason about it
to move forward we introduce a model a model acts as a bridge between reality and numbers
it
defines rules, abstractions and assumptions. Instead of dealing with raw
observations, we decide what matters, what we want to measure and how different
observations are related. Without this step, any number we produce would be
arbitrary. Once the model is defined, we can assign numbers. These numbers are not
random. They represent structures, metrics that follow the rules of the model. If
the model is weak or unclear, the numbers will be misleading. If the model is sound,
the numbers become meaningful and useful for
analysis, prediction and decision-making. The key idea here is the transition from
intuition to reward. Rather than relying on personal judgments or information
opinions, software measurement aims to create objective, repeatable and
defensible results. This is the foundation of the model.
This is the foundation for valid metrics, reliable predictions and better engineering
decisions later in the course.
So, let me come to the second slide, because unfortunately I don't have a mouse. Oh, sorry
about that. Yes.
The trap of native measurements.
Yes.
In software engineering, using numbers can feel safe and objective. However, numbers
alone do not always give real understanding. A common example is Fouls per kilo. At first
gallons, this metric looks simple and useful, but its meaning changes depending on what
we are trying to say.
The goals of the metric test are in the following categories.
When the focus is on the testing process, Fouls per kilo can be helpful.
In this case, the goal is to understand how often defects are discovered. A higher number
may indicate active and effective testing. Here, the metric supports the attributes we care about,
so it works well the situation changes when we look at tester efficiency comparing
comparing two testers using false ignores program complexity one tester may work on a very complex
system while the other works on a simple one the numbers may look comparable but the conclusion
would be unfair in this context the metric give gives a wrong signal the biggest risk
appears when faults per kilo is used for code quality a system with many detected faults
may actually
have better quality because it was tested more truly another system may show fever faults simply
because the problems may look comparable but the conclusion would be unfair in this context
the metric gives a wrong signal the biggest risk appears when faults is used for
code quality a system with many detected faults may fault mean mistake right a system with yes
a system with yes it's my with many detected false they may have maybe a better quality
because it was tested more truly yes the system may have many faults but because of that best quality
because it was tested more truly, it may be better.
Another system may show fever faults
simply because problems were not found yet.
In this case, the metric can easily mislead decision makers.
The main lesson is simple.
Numbers do not automatically create insights.
Before measuring, we must clearly define
what entity we are studying
and which attributes we want to understand.
Only in this case, the metric can easily mislead decision makers.
Only they can metric become meaningful
and trustworthy.
The next slide.
I don't have mouse, so I'm encountering some difficulties
to use that, unfortunately.
How can I do that?
Okay, here I think.
Model is an abstract of reality.
In measurements, we never work with reality exactly as it is.
Instead, we create a model.
A model helps us remove unnecessary detail
and focus only on what matters for our goal.
This makes complex things easier to understand and compare.
Think about measuring a person's height.
Small decisions change the results.
Do we include shows or not?
What about hair?
Is the person standing straight or not?
Each choice affects the final number.
Before using the ruler,
we must agree on these rules.
Without them, the measurement has no clear meaning.
The same idea applies to software,
especially when we talk about lines of code,
LOC, lines of code.
Several questions appear immediately.
Should commands be counted?
Do data declarations matter?
What if multiple statements are written on the same line?
So, different answers lead to different numbers,
even for the same program.
This is why the model is important.
The number itself is not the problem.
The problem is using a number
without clearly defining the model behind it.
If the rules are unclear,
comparisons become unreliable
and conclusions become weak.
So, the key idea is simple.
Before measuring software,
we must first decide what we include,
what we ignore, and why.
Only then can a metric represent reality.
Even a metric represents reality
in a useful and consistent way.
So, let's skip the other slides.
Imagine a dog that is very intelligent.
We have a dog that is very intelligent.
Let's assume that this dog understands people.
It solves problems
and reacts correctly in many situations.
It's very clever.
However, this dog cannot read or write.
Now, think about giving this dog
a written IQ test.
We assume that we have given to the dog
an IQ test.
And the result will be what?
The result will be zero.
Even though the dog is clearly smart.
This situation shows a serious measurement problem.
The mistake is not in the dog.
The mistake is in the measurement method.
We focused only on the formal system.
The tests,
but clearly defining
what we really wanted to measure in the world,
which is intelligence.
Here the empirical attribute is intelligence.
But intelligence has many aspects.
Problem solving,
learning,
adaptation and understanding.
Writing ability is only one smart part.
When the model ignores these other aspects,
the number no longer represents reality.
This leads to an important lesson
for software measurements.
If we jump directly to numbers
without defining the attribute clearly,
the results can be misleading.
A valid measure needs a well-defined model
that connects real-world characteristics
to numbers in a meaningful way.
So, the key message is simple.
If the attribute is not clearly defined
in the real world,
any number we assign to it
becomes meaningless,
no matter how precise it looks.
The next slide will be
Illusion of Complexity.
Let's look at here.
In this study,
we look at a very well-known software metric,
McCabe's Psylomatic Number.
It is shown as V .
This metric is often used
to talk about software complexity.
The formula is basic
and it is shown in two ways.
First, V is equal to
e minus n plus 2,
where e means edges
and n means nodes
in a control flow graph.
Second, the same value is written as
V equals to d plus 1,
where d is the number of decision nodes
in the program.
The common assumption is very clear.
When the value of V is high,
the program is seen as
fault-prone and hard to maintain.
Many people directly connect
a high Psylomatic Number
with high complexity.
But the reality is more subtle.
Psylomatic Number is mainly
a count of decisions.
It tells us how many different paths
exist in the code.
A program can contain
many decision points
and still be easy to read
and easy to understand.
And because of this,
we must be careful
with interpretation.
Psylomatic complexity
is a valid measure of decisions,
but it's only a partial measure
of complexity.
It does not capture readability,
structure, naming,
or design quality.
So the key lesson in this,
Psylomatic Number gives
useful information,
but when it is used alone
to represent complexity,
it can be misleading.
Numbers are helpful,
but only when we clearly understand
what they really measure.
We need to be careful about this.
So the next slide,
I think it is
Direct vs. Derived
Measurement.
In this slide,
we focus on the mechanics
of measurements.
Specifically, we compare
direct measurements
and derivative measurements.
First, let's look at
direct measurements.
A direct measurement involves
no other attribute.
We measure one thing directly
without using another value.
The most common example is length.
Measures with a ruler.
In software,
similar direct measurements
are source code size,
LOC,
defect count,
and testing hours.
Each of these values
is observed
and counted directly.
Now, let's look
to the derivative measures
of measurements.
A derivative measurement
is defined in terms
of other attributes.
This means we calculate it
by combining two or more
direct measurements.
The classic example is
density.
It is defined as
mass divided by volume,
as you know.
In software,
we use the same idea.
For example,
programmer productivity
is measured as
LOC per person amount.
Another example is
defect density,
defined as defects divided
by model size.
The key point is shown
in the sentence
at the bottom of this slide.
Derivative measurement
makes visible
the interactions
between attributes.
It helps us understand
relationships,
not just row numbers.
So,
direct measures
tell us what exists,
while derivative measures
help us understand
how things relate
to each other.
Both are important
by they serve
different purposes
in software
managements.
And next slide
is about
hidden hotspots.
In this slide,
we see
how derivative measures
can reveal problems
that direct measures hide.
The title already gives us
the idea.
Revealing the hidden hotspots.
Let us first look at
the chart on the left,
on the left side of the slide.
This chart shows
a direct measure,
total faults.
It's on the left.
It's on my left,
but it may change to you.
Maybe it may on your right,
but please read the title.
Total faults.
It shows a direct measure
of total faults.
Each bar represents
a subsystem
from A to P.
And the height of the bar
shows the total number
of faults.
Faults means mistake
or
mistake, yes.
Faults.
If we only look
at this chart,
subsystem A
does not look very dangerous.
Some other subsystems
have many more total faults.
So,
based on this direct measure,
we might decide to focus
on those larger bars.
Now,
let's look at the chart
on the right.
This chart shows
a derivative measure,
faults per clock.
Here,
the number of faults
is divided
by the size of the code.
This changes the picture completely.
Subsystem A
suddenly stands out
very clearly.
Even though
it has fewer total faults,
it has the highest
fault density.
This message
at the bottom of the slide
explains,
if you can,
if you are able to read it.
Subsystem A
is only
4000 lines of code,
but it has the highest
density.
It means
it is the real risk.
So,
the key
lesson is simple
but very important.
Total faults
show quantity.
But faults per clock
show risk.
Derivative messages
help us find
hidden hotspots
that direct measures
cannot solve.
This is why
derivative measurements
are so powerful
in software measurements.
They help us
make better
and more
important
decisions.
Okay,
next slide.
Okay.
In this slide,
we move from
assessment
to prediction.
These two ideas
are related
by,
but
they
are not
the same.
First,
look at
the
left side
of the slide.
This part
represents
assessments.
Assessment means
measuring
what already
exists.
Okay.
So,
assessment
means
it has
a meaning
that we
measure
what
already
exists.
Here,
we see
a globe
with two cities.
For example,
DC
and London.
Using the
globe,
we can measure
the known
distance
between
these two points.
This distance
already exists
in the
real world,
but
and
we
still
simply
measure
it.
So,
assessment
is
about
current
and known
attributes.
We
observe
something
real
and we
describe
it
using
numbers.
Now,
let us
move
to the
right side
of the
slide.
This part
represents
a prediction
that
does not
yet
exist.
Prediction,
as we
understand
from the
name,
make a
prediction.
Here,
we
are
no longer
measuring
a known
distance.
Instead,
we
are
estimating
a future
journey.
For
example,
how
long
is the
future?
This is
where the
dashed
arrow is
important.
It shows
that
prediction
goes
beyond
the
known
world.
The
key
sentence
at the
bottom
explains
the main
idea.
It is
written
in
the
red
color.
Prediction
attributes
in the
future.
In software
measurement,
this is
very
important.
We
first
need
valid
assessment
measures.
Only
then
can
we
build
reliable
prediction
models.
So,
the
main
lesson
is
that
prediction
uses
models
to
estimate
what
does
not
yet
exist.
Anatomy
of
prediction
system.
In
the
slides,
we
look at
the
anatomy
of a
prediction
system.
This
means
we
know
that
the
model
is
written
as a
simple
formula.
Cost
t
equals
a
times
b
over
c.
This
formula
is
not
random.
It
shows
how
prediction
uses
mathematical
relationship.
For example,
from London
to
Bristol
or
from
Istanbul
to
Bursa.
B
is
the
cost
per
gallon
and
C
is
the
miles
per
gallon
which
tells
us
fuel
efficiency.
These
parameters
do
not
exist
in
the
model
slide.
Prediction
producers
answer
an
important
question.
How
do
we
determine
the
values
first
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
B?
The
second
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
B?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values of
C?
The
third
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values of
C?
The
fifth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fifth
question
is
what
are
the
values of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fourth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fifth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fifth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
fifth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
values of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
seventh
question
is
what
are
the
values
of
C?
The
sixth
question
is
what
are
the
As we move to the right, the scale becomes richer and more sophisticated.
At the same time, the rules become more restrictive.
Let's start from the left.
The first scale is nominal.
Nominal scales are only labels.
They allow us to say difference or same, but nothing more.
There is no order and no size.
Next is the ordinal scale.
Here we can rank the things.
We know which one is higher or lower, but we do not know the exact distance between them.
After that comes the interval scale.
With interval scales...
Differences matter.
The distance between values is meaningful.
However, there is still no true zero.
Then we have the ratio scale after that.
The scale has true zero.
Because of that, ratios like twice as much are meaningful.
At the top, we see the difference.
Absolute scale.
This is the strongest scale.
Counting items is a typical example.
On the right side of the slide, we see an important definition.
A scale is made of three parts.
The mapping.
The empirical system.
And the numerical system.
Below that, we see the term admissible transformation.
This means the rules that allow us to change one measurement in another.
For example, from inches to centimeters.
Without losing meaning.
The key idea here is simple but very important.
Not every operation is allowed on every scale.
If we use the wrong scale, our analysis can become meaningless.
So, before measuring or analyzing data, we must always ask...
Which measurement scale am I using?
So, let me go through another slide.
Numeral scales are used for classification only.
They separate items into different classes.
Each class represents a different type, such as specification files, design files, and code files.
These categories are distinct, but they are not ordered.
There is no meaning of more or less in nominal scales.
A design file is not greater than a code file.
They are simply different kinds.
The numbers used in nominal scales are labels only.
They do not represent size, distance, or priority.
Because of this, numbers can be changed freely.
As long as each label stays unique.
For example, one category can be mapped from 1 to 101.
Another from 2 to 69.
And another from 3 to 73.
This kind of change is allowed because it is a one-to-one transformation.
The key idea is here.
It is simple.
Nominal scales answer the question...
Are these the same or different?
They do not answer which is better or which is larger.
Only it asks are these the same or different.
Maybe...
No, it's not the last slide.
Only we have two or more, maybe.
Oops.
Yes.
Ordinal scales are used for ranking.
They make nominal categories and add order to them.
A common example is severity levels.
Low severity comes before medium severity.
Yes.
It comes before medium severity.
A medium severity comes before high severity.
This ordering is meaningful.
High severity is worse than medium severity.
And medium severity is worse than low severity.
However, the size of the difference is unknown.
It's possible to say that high severity is twice as bad as medium severity.
Because of this, arithmetic operations have no meaning.
Addition and subtraction do not make sense here.
Only the order matters, not the distance between levels.
The allowed transformation must preserve the order.
Numbers can change, but the ranking must stay the same.
The key question answered by ordinal scales is quite simple.
Which comes before and which comes after?
They do not answer how much worse.
This is the last slide.
But don't worry, I have other slides.
Actually, I was planning to make this presentation at the previous week,
second week, but we didn't get time for this,
so I have shifted this presentation to this week.
But anyway, we have to finish all these slides last week
or this week or next week.
Doesn't matter.
Yes, let me make some arrangements.
Yes, that's all.
Regions measurement, it's a summary, text summary.
The regions measurement follows a clear path, not a shortcut.
The first step is to define the model.
We must be clear about what we are measuring
and which attributes we care about.
Without this, numbers have no meaning.
Next, we verify representation.
The numbers must reflect what we observe in the real world.
If the numbers contradict reality, the measure is wrong.
After that, we can use derived measures.
Derived measures help reveal relationships between attributes,
not just isolated values.
Once reliable measures exist, prediction systems become possible.
Prediction always depends on a model and clear procedures.
Without both, predictions are guesswork.
Finally, we must respect the measurement scale.
Nominal and ordinal data do not allow the same operations as ratio data.
Using the wrong scale leads to wrong conclusions.
OK, idea here.
Measurement is not only about collecting data.
It's about mapping real-world observations
in a numerical system that we can understand and trust.
So, I think the number of slides was 13 or 14.
We have finished.
I think I have a summary of these slides.
Maybe if I could find...
I can...
Yes, now let me make a brief summary of what we have studied with these slides.
And after that, we will skip to the other slides I have.
In this presentation, from the beginning,
we introduced a conceptual framework that connected all the slides
and explained how so they're located.
And how software measurements moved from intuition
toward a more religious and scientific approach.
The main idea was the measurement was not merely about producing numbers,
but about establishing a meaningful relationship
between real-world software phenomena and numerical representations.
These slides emphasized the importance of defining the measurement model first,
particularly the entity-attribute pair.
Through several examples,
these presentations showed that commonly used metrics,
such as false per-clock or silomatic complexity,
were only meaningful
when their assumptions and contexts were clearly defined.
Otherwise, the same metric could lead to correct conclusions in one case
and misleading interpretations in another.
Later, the presentation distinguished between direct and real messages
and demonstrated
how derived metrics revealed hidden problems
that raw counts could not expose.
It then moved from assessment to prediction,
where prediction was shown to rely on mathematical models,
assumptions about future behavior,
and careful interpretation of uncertainty.
Finally,
the presentation introduced measurement scales
and explained
why respecting their limitations
was essential for valid analysis.
Overall,
the presentation,
from the beginning until now,
demonstrated that
religious software measurement required
a structured process,
defining models,
validating representations,
using appropriate measures,
building prediction systems,
and respecting measurement scales.
This summary captured the main ideas
that tied all slides together into a coherent whole.
Okay, friends,
after making this summary,
I have prepared some new presentations
for the other lectures.
So let me try to open it
because it's difficult to use pads of the laptop
because I forget my mouse in somewhere.
Yes, this is first.
Let me open.
The pages were,
I think,
62 and 76.
And here we are skipping to page numbers
from 76 to 92.
I think that is,
yes.
So the slide number,
let me take,
okay, let me first stop the sharing
and share the new documents.
Try to do that.
And it will take a few seconds.
Measurement is the mapping of reality to numbers.
But I think I need to make it a little bit smaller.
Can it be seen clearly?
But it is,
I'm looking for,
how can it be?
Please give me some time.
So the size of the slides are so big.
I think you are not able to see the whole page.
Yes, I found.
I'm going to the first slide.
Strange.
Okay, maybe this is better.
Yes.
Arrange the camera.
When we talk about measurements,
we are really talking about a mapping.
On one side,
there is the messy,
complicated,
empirical world.
Code,
bugs,
entities,
user behavior,
system states,
even noise,
and unstructured data.
These things,
exist before any number appears.
They are real,
observable,
and often ambitious.
Then we create a bridge
to the formal world,
to mathematics.
Here,
everything becomes
symbols,
values,
comparisons,
calculations.
The moment we define a scale,
m,
we decide how something from reality
will be translated into numbers.
If the bridge is well designed,
the numbers will correctly represent
what is happening in reality.
If it is badly designed,
we may compute perfectly
and still be wrong.
Okay?
So,
the big question in software metrics is
never only
what number did we get.
The real question is
whether the mapping
between the attributes
and the value
follows the correct rules.
Once we understand that,
we can decide
which operations,
comparisons,
and statistics
are actually legitimate.
Without that understanding,
without that understanding,
if we do not understand this,
numbers may look
scientific,
but carry no real meaning.
Let's go to the second slide,
slide number two.
Yes.
Now the key idea
becomes sharper.
Admissible transformations.
A measurement scale is defined
by transformations
we can apply
without destroying the real-world meaning.
Look at the ratio scale
example with height.
You can see on the slide.
Fred is taller than Jane.
If we measure in feet,
the statement is true.
If we convert to meters,
multiplying by,
I think it was 1.3,
approximately,
1.0,
sorry,
0.3,
yes.
We are trying to convert it.
If we try to convert to meters,
we need to multiply it by 0.3.
In this case,
the statement is still true.
Nothing about reality changes.
The relationship survives the transformation.
Because the truth is preserved,
the statement is meaningful.
Now,
compare this with temperature
on the interval scale.
In Celsius,
40 degrees Celsius,
in Tokyo,
looks like twice 20 degrees in London.
But,
after transforming to Fahrenheit,
104 Fahrenheit
is not twice 68 Fahrenheit.
The numbers changed in a legal way,
yet the ratio disappeared.
That's a
That tells us something very important.
The claim,
twice as hot,
was never stable.
Yes.
Twice as hot was never stable.
It depended on the choice of units.
When truth changes after transformation,
the statement is meaningless.
So,
admissible transformations work,
like stress tests.
If a conclusion survives
every allowed change of scale,
we can trust it.
If it collapses,
it was only an illusion
created by the numbers.
This principle will guide everything that comes next,
especially
when deciding which mathematical operations
are safe to use.
Yes,
let's go through
slide number three,
nominal scale.
Let's begin with level one,
It's the most basic form
of
form of measurements.
The goal here is simply
is simply classification.
We put entities into different buckets,
such as specification files,
design files,
or code files.
The numbers
or labels we
attach
are just names.
They do not say anything about importance,
size, or severity.
They only help us
distinguish one category
from another.
Yet,
what does the nominal scale preserve?
It preserves identity.
If two items
are different in reality,
they stay different
after measurements.
That is all.
But because of this,
the admissible transformation
is a one-to-one mapping.
We can rename category one
as 101,
or 500,
or blue,
or triangle.
It does not matter.
As long as each class
remains separate,
the meaning is safe.
But the constraints
are very strict.
We cannot add,
we cannot subtract,
and we definitely
cannot rank
specific constraints.
Seeing design files
are greater than code files
would be inventing information
that the scale simply
does not contain.
So,
when our data is only labeling
or grouping,
we are living in the nominal world.
The moment
we try to do arithmetic,
we step outside
what is legitimate.
Yes.
Okay.
I think we need to
go to the next slide.
We climb,
now we climb to level two,
the ordinal scale.
The ordinal scale keeps
everything we had
in the nominal scale,
but it adds something powerful.
Ordering.
It is ordering.
Yes.
We can now say
one class is more
than another.
For instance,
trivial,
simple,
moderate,
complex,
incomprehensible.
We know
the direction
of growth.
But there is a catch.
We know
who is higher.
Yet,
we do not
know
the
direction
of growth.
But there is a catch.
We know
who
is higher.
Yet,
we do
not
know
by
how much.
Think of it
like a
staircase.
Someone
standing
on a higher
step
is above you.
Yes.
But
are the steps
one meter
apart
or one centimeter?
The scale
does not
tell
us this.
The distance
between levels
is
unknown.
What does
this
scale
preserve?
It preserves
rank.
If
a
was
above
b
before
measurement,
a
must remain
above
b
after
measurement.
The requirement
defines
the
admissible
transformation.
Any
monotonic
increasing
function
is
allowed.
You
can
estimate
the
distance
from the
top
to the
bottom
of the
scale.
The
distance
from
top
to
bottom
is
0.1
.
The
distance
from
bottom
distance
we must resist because distances are undefined, addition and subtraction are meaningless.
The difference between complex and moderate is not guaranteed to equal the difference between
simple and trivial. Therefore, statements like twice as complex or computing an average level
are dangerous. What can we safely do? We can compare, we can rank, we can say higher
or lower, we can say before or after. We can also use statistics that depend on the order,
like the median or percentiles. So, the ordinal scale gives us more analytical
power in order to give other determinants the same algorithmic value. So, the ordinal scale has
than nominal, but it still blocks arithmetic with distances.
Let me open the other slides.
Excellent. Now we reach level 3, interval scale,
where measurement becomes much stronger.
Here we still keep the order from the ordinal level,
but we gain something new and very important.
We understand the size of the jump between values.
If the distance between 10 and 20 is the same as between 20 and 30,
the quantity of difference is meaningful.
The scale now preserves distances.
A good way to picture this is with the two rulers in the future.
One person starts counting from April 1,
another from January 1.
Their zeros are different,
but the gap between day 10 and day 20 is identical in both systems.
So in interval, the distance survives.
This idea defines the admissible transformation.
We are allowed to multiply by constant,
A, and also add or subtract A constant B.
Means the zero point can move because zero can shift.
Ratios become...
Sorry about that.
What was I saying?
Yes, the zero point can move because zero can shift.
Ratios become unreliable.
If I can freely move zero,
how could twice as much remain stable?
So we can safely say how far apart two values are.
Whether one increases equals another,
we can add or subtract,
but we cannot say twice as early,
twice as hot,
half as large.
We cannot say that.
The zero is arbitrary,
but not a true absence of the attribute.
This is why Celsius and Fahrenheit work perfectly
for differences in temperature,
but fail completely for ratios.
Slight number.
I think it was 86.
Sorry, it was level four.
I think...
Okay.
Ratio scale.
This is level four ratio scale,
the point where measurement reaches its full strength.
Like the interval scale,
we still preserve order and differences,
but now we gain the most powerful ingredients,
a true zero.
Zero means a complete absence of the attributes,
no lengths,
no time,
no defects,
no lines of code,
or nothing.
Because zero is real and fixed,
ratios become stable.
If program B has 200 lines
and program A has 100 lines,
then B is twice A.
That statement will remain true
no matter how we change the units.
Convert lines to understand
to thousands of lines
or to characters using a constant multiplier,
the relationship survive.
This is why the admissible transformation is simpler
than in the interval case.
We can multiply by a constant A,
but we are not allowed to add anything.
This formula, as you see,
M equals A, M, M.
The intercept B must be zero.
If we add a constant,
we would move zero,
and then ratios would collapse.
Thanks to the true zero,
multiplication and division finally make sense.
We can say twice as large,
half as long,
three times faster.
All these comparisons are legitimate
because empirical meaning is preserved
under every allowed transformation.
So the ratio scale opens the door
to the richest mathematical analysis.
And the hero behind this power is simple.
Zero actually means zero.
Now we have level five.
Let's finish level five,
and after that,
let's continue next week.
The absolute scale,
the strictest of all.
Here, measurement becomes pure counting.
We are not estimating size, distance,
or intensity.
We are simply asking how many.
For example, how many failures occurred.
The answer might be 12,
and the number is not negotiable.
It cannot be discussed.
Because we are counting actual occurrences.
There is only one possible correct value.
You cannot remap 12
into 50,
or 3,
or multiply it by something.
Any change would immediately break reality.
That is why the admissible transformation
is only the identity.
No conversion,
no shifting,
no rescaling.
The value is the value.
Think about we cannot measure failures
in meters, kilograms, or degrees.
Failures are not length or temperature.
They are events.
So the only legitimate measurement
is the number of failures.
Now, here comes an important phenomenon
that often confuses people.
Take lines of code,
NoC.
If we are talking about program length,
NoC behaves like a ratio scale.
Because we could transform it
to thousands of lines or characters
with multiplication.
If the attribute is the number of lines,
then it is absolute.
A program has exactly that many lines,
and there is only one way to count them.
So the absolute scale is extremely powerful
in certainty,
but extremely limited in flexibility.
No alternative mapping exists.
Now let's stop here, my friends.
It's enough for this week.
We are at number,
slide number eight,
and I will take notes here
in order not to forget where we are.
So we will continue from these slides.
Okay.
Now, I think it's enough.
See you next week, my friends.
Take care of yourself.
Bye.