This is not our course. I want to make a technical check. Please write something on the chat box whether there is a problem or not. Can you hear my voice clearly or not? Please. If you can hear me, just write OK.
Is there anyone there? I think I cannot see anyone. Anyway, let me start my course. Maybe some friends do not know that we will start our course this week.
So, since this video will be recorded, anyone can watch it later.
OK.
Now,
before I start with the slides, I would like to give a brief overview of this course.
Titled, as you know, Software Matrix.
Software Matrix. Yes, let me check again.
Not anyone. OK.
This course, in fact, focuses on how software systems,
software processes and
development processes
and activities
can be measured in a
systematic and meaningful
way.
In software engineering,
we often deal with
abstract concepts
such as
quality, complexity,
productivity,
reliability and
or maintainability.
These concepts
are critical
for decision making,
yet,
they are frequently discussed
in subjective terms.
The goal of the software
matrix course is
to show that
these aspects of
software can be
qualified using
well-defined matrix
models
and
measurement principles.
Throughout this course,
we will study why
measurement is
necessary, what can
be measured in software
and
how measurement supports
engineering decisions
at difficult
levels.
Also, including project management,
development
and quality
assurance.
OK.
Can you hear me, Murtaza?
I see you on the
online, I see you
only you are
available. If you can
hear me just right, OK.
OK, anyway. This
course does not aim to promote
measuring everything.
Instead,
it emphasizes
measuring the right
attributes for a
clear purpose
in order to reduce
uncertainty and
support informed
decisions.
We will examine
software matrix from
multiple perspectives
such as management,
developers
and organizations.
We will
see how matrix are
used across
the software life
cycle. By the end,
of this course, you
should understand
how software matrix
help transform
software developments
from a largely
intuition-driven
activity into
a more predictable,
controllable and
engineering-oriented
discipline. With this
overview in mind,
we can now
move to
the core concepts
of software
management.
Now, let me give you
an information relating to the
documents, my friends. Every
week, I will
try to put my
PPT slides on
the system. I will
put
the main
documents, which chapters
will be studied in the main
document and the relating
PowerPoint files
will be
put in the
system. Week by week,
I will try to do that. So,
before the course
starts, maybe
it's better
to
at least
read one or
two times before the course
starts. It will help you
to understand better.
In the examination, we
need to
read all the
documents in order
to remind the
points in your mind.
It will be enough,
I think. Otherwise,
if you collect all
the chapters,
it is almost impossible
to study all the chapters
in only one week.
It will be
bad for you.
Now, let's
put my slides.
Let me share my
slides here.
Let's begin.
Continue our course.
Yes, Eren, can you hear me?
We couldn't check
anything. We couldn't make
any technical check.
I see Murtaza, Eren,
Karaca is writing.
I see that.
Otherwise, sometimes
there occurs
some voice problem. I'm speaking
the course.
Sorry about that.
I'm a little bit ill today.
So,
whenever
there is a voice problem,
I realize that at the end of the video.
So, it will be better to
make a control check now.
Yes, you can.
Okay, thank you, Murtaza.
So, I
cannot see clearly what you are
reading, I think.
There is a windowing
problem. Okay, now
let me share my slides.
And after that
we will continue.
Excuse me.
Software matrix.
I'm trying to
share software
matrix.
Software matrix.
Yes.
Week one.
Qualifying software engineering.
It will take
a few seconds.
Also, whenever you have any questions,
you can send me email.
I will try to answer all the
emails.
You know my email.
In the system
you can find it.
Okay, this is my
PowerPoint.
I think you can see
clearly, but
yes, it's better, I think.
I'm trying to
adjust