Good morning, can you hear me? I think that you can hear me because I cannot see any problem. The microphone is okay and the video is okay. So let me first share my document and after that we continue our course this week.
Yes, software matrix. This is the week number five, as I remember. Yes, absolutely. It will take a few seconds and after that we can make our course.
I'm asking again, is there any problem? Can you hear me? Depending on the speed of the internet, the upload process will take a few seconds.
We need to be patient. So let me arrange the position. Yes, the title will be the geometry of software measurements.
The geometry of software measurements. But the uploading process is going on at that moment. I think it's okay.
The geometry of software measurements.
Today,
we begin with the idea of geometry of software measurement.
This title is interesting because it suggests that software measurement is not random.
It's not random. It has structure. It has dimensions. It has relationships.
Just like geometry studies,
shapes,
and dimensions.
Just like it, software measurement studies different aspects of development in an organized way.
The subtitle at the bottom of the main title gives the core idea, a goal-based framework for classifying,
process,
products,
and resources.
These three elements,
process,
products,
and resource,
form the foundation of how we measure software systems.
Let's start with process first.
A process represents activities over time.
It includes development steps like requirements analysis, design, coding, testing, or maintenance.
In measurement terms, we often look at duration, effort, cost, or number of defects found during a process.
Processes are dynamic.
They involve workflow transformation and input turning into output.
Next, we have product.
A product is any artifact produced during the software lifecycle.
It can be source code,
design diagrams,
test cases,
documentation,
or the final software system.
Products can be measured using attributes like size,
complexity,
modularity,
reliability,
or maintainability.
Some of these are internal attributes,
like lines of code.
Others are external,
or external attributes,
like usability or performance.
And finally, we consider resources.
Resources include people.
Resources, yes,
include people and tools,
hardware,
methods,
and teams.
These are the inputs used to produce software.
We measure resources in terms of costs.
In terms of costs,
experience level,
productivity,
or skill utilization.
If we give an example,
productivity is often calculated as output divided by effort.
It connects product measurements with process measurements.
What is powerful here is the goal-based idea.
We do not measure everything.
We measure what supports our goals.
If our goal is improving reliability,
we select metrics
that relate to faults,
failures,
and defect detection.
If our goal is improving productivity,
we focus on effort and output ratios.
So,
instead of measuring randomly,
this framework gives us structure.
It tells us to first
classify what we are measuring
or process,
product,
or resources.
And then
define metrics
that align with our goals.
This geometric perspective
helps us think in dimensions.
Every measurement belongs somewhere
in the structured space.
And understanding
that structure
is the first step towards meaningful
and valid software measurements.
Now we move to a very important principle.
Measurement requires classification.
We often say we want quality.
We want better software.
Fewer bugs.
Higher reliability.
Lower costs.
But the word quality is abstract.
It's vojo.
If we do not define it properly,
we cannot measure it.
It needs to be defined properly.
And if it cannot be defined properly,
we cannot measure it.
And if we cannot measure it,
we cannot control it.
So,
this slide introduces
a key measurement rule.
You cannot set a meaningful goal
until you identify two things.
The entity
and the attributes.
First,
the entity.
Let's study the entity.
What is entity?
The entity is the thing
we are measuring.
It could be a process
like testing,
for example.
Or it could be a product
like source code.
Or it could be a resource
like a development team.
Second,
the attributes.
What is attributes?
The attribute is the property
of that entity.
If we do an example,
if the entity is code,
the attribute could be the size
or complexity
and reliability
or maintainability.
If the entity is a testing process,
so the attributes
could be cost
or duration
or effectiveness.
Without clearly separating
entity and attributes,
we mix concepts.
For example,
saying we want better quality.
It is not enough.
Saying that is not enough.
Better quality of what?
Code.
You mean code?
You mean design
or testing process?
And which aspects?
Reliability?
Usability?
Or cost effectiveness?
What do you mean?
The image in the slides
in the center
acts like a classification.
A classification filter.
Many terms
such as cost,
speed,
comfort,
reliability,
maintainability
and bugs
are flowing into the system.
But before measuring,
we must filter them.
So,
before the measuring process,
we must use the filtering process.
We must organize them
into a structured measurement framework.
This is where classification
becomes essential.
It moves us from emotional goals
to concrete geometry.
Instead of saying
we want fewer bugs,
we define entity
the software products
attributes number of defects
per kilo.
Now the goal
becomes measurable.
So, the main idea
is discipline.
Measurement is not about
collecting numbers randomly.
It is about defining clearly
what is the entity,
what is the attribute.
Only after that
can we select proper metrics
and set meaningful goals.
Yes.
The three software entities.
Now we focus
on the core structure
of software measurements.
The three software entities.
Everything in this framework
revolves around
three fundamental elements.
Resources,
processes
and products.
These are not random categories.
They represent
the full lifecycle
of software development
in a silical model.
Let's start with resources.
It is input.
Resources are the entities
required to perform an activity.
These include people,
teams,
tools,
hardware,
software platforms
and methods.
Without resources
nothing happens.
They are the inputs
of the
the input size
of the system.
When we measure resources
we might look at costs.
Also we might look at
experience level
and team size.
Scale distribution
or tool capability.
Next,
we move to process activity.
Processes are software related activities
that occur over time.
Designing,
coding,
testing,
maintaining.
These are all processes.
They transform
inputs
into outputs.
Processes have duration,
efforts,
sequence
and structure.
When measuring processes
we focus on time,
we focus on costs,
we focus on number of
defects found
and also efficiency
and we focus on
cost effectiveness.
Then we arrive at
products,
means outputs.
Products are the artifacts
and deliverables
produced by processes.
These include
design documents,
include also
source code,
classifications,
test cases
and
the final system.
Products are often
easier to examine directly.
We can measure size,
complexity,
modularity,
coupling,
reliability
or maintainability.
What makes this model powerful
is its
silent nature.
Resources enable processes.
Processes generate products.
Products may require
new processes for
maintenance or evolution.
And updated products
may require
new or improved
resources.
This means
measurement cannot focus
on only one dimension.
If product quality
is low,
the issue may,
the issue might not be
in the product itself.
It could be in the process
or it could be
in the resources.
For example,
insufficient experience
or inadequate tools.
So when defining
measurement goals,
we must first ask,
are we analyzing
a resource problem,
a process problem
or a product problem?
This structured
classification ensures
that our measurement system
covers the complete geometry
or software development.
Yes.
Now,
we look at
a measurement from two
different perspectives
or,
as the title says,
two lenses of measurement,
internal attributes
and external attributes.
Internal attributes
Let's begin
with internal attributes.
Internal attributes
are measured purely
in terms of the entity itself.
They do not depend
on how the software
behaves in real usage.
They are static.
That means we can measure
them without executing
the system.
For instance,
if we look
at source code,
we can measure
code size,
such as lines of code,
complexity,
such as number of
decision points,
modularity,
coupling of
or cohesion.
All of these are
internal product attributes.
We simply inspect
the artifacts.
We do not need users.
We do not need
runtime behavior.
Internal attributes
focus on structure.
Yes,
it focuses
on structure.
Now,
let's move
to external attributes.
They depend
on how
the entity
relates
to its environment.
They are
behavioral.
That means
we must
observe
the system
in operation
to measure them.
Examples include
reliability.
We often
how
often
the system
fails
during use.
And usability.
How easily
users
interact
with it.
And cost
effectiveness.
How much
value
we obtain
compared
to resources
spent.
These attributes
cannot be
measured
by reading
code alone.
We must
consider
context,
configuration,
users
and
operational
conditions.
This distinction
is extremely
important
in software
measurements.
Managers
and users
are often
more
interested
in
internal
attributes
because
they
directly
affect
real-world
performance.
However,
external
attributes
are
harder
to measure
and
usually
appear
later
in the
development
life cycle.
Developers
often
rely
on
internal
attributes
as
indicators.
For example,
high
complexity
may
suggest
lower
maintainability.
Strong
modularity
may
suggest
better
reliability,
but the
relationship
is not
always
guaranteed.
That is
why validation
is
critical.
So,
when we
define a
measurement
goal,
we must
ask
are we
measuring
structure
or are
we
measuring
behavior?
Are
we
measuring
structure
or
behavior?
Understanding
these
two
lenses
help
us
interpret
metrics
correctly
and
avoid
misleading
conclusions.
To
better
understand
the
relationship
between
internal
attributes
and
external
attributes,
let's
look at
the
main
concern
of
reliability.
You
want
to
know
whether
the
car
will
perform
well
over
time.
Reliability
here is
an
external
attribute.
It
depends
on
how
the
car
behaves
in
under heavy
load
over
months
of usage.
But
there is a
problem.
You cannot
test drive
the car
for six
months
before buying
it.
You cannot
observe
its
long-term
behavior.
So
how do
you make
a decision?
You
examine
internal
attributes
instead.
You
check
tire
thread
depth.
You
look
at
brake
condition.
You
observe
structural
aspects
of
the
car.
These
are
static
properties.
They
do
not
require
long-term
driving
to
measure.
So
these
internal
attributes
do not
directly
measure
reliability.
But
they help
you to
predict
it.
If
the
tire
wear
is
uneven,
that
might
indicate
poor
maintenance,
if
the
oil
is
dirty,
that
means
the tire
is
damaged.
So
you
have
to
look
at
the
tire
length
and
the
tire
length
and
the
tire
length
and
the
tire
length
and
the
tire
length
in
the
original
content.
We
cannot
always
observe
long-term
reliability
during
the
development
stages.
So
instead
we
measure
internal
structure
as we
did
in
buying
the
used
car.
These
are
modularity, coupling and cohesion, number of detected faults, these are the internal structure.
So as a summary, in order to make sure whether our software is reliable,
we look at the internal structure instead of external attributes.
Because external attributes depend on runtime behavior, user interaction, and operational contexts.
We cannot, it is not possible always to observe long-term reliability.
So instead of trying to measure reliability as it is external attribute,
we look at its internal structure as code complexity, modularity, coupling, and number of detected faults.
These internal measures help us predict the future behavior or the future condition.
Just like checking oil and tire condition
inspecting cold structure gives us only signals about maintainability and reliability.
These are extremely important concepts.
However, it is important to remember that prediction is not proof.
Internal attributes suggest possible outcomes, possible results.
But,
they do not guarantee them.
That is why understanding the relationship between structure and behavior is critical in measurement research.
This analogy reminds us that internal measurements are often used as predictors of external quantity.
And in practice, this is how software quantity,
control works.
Okay.
It's a little bit cold here still.
So, I am taking an action.
Excuse me for that.
In the morning, this place becomes cold in general.
But afternoon, it will be okay.
So, we are at slide six.
Okay.
Slide number six.
Yes.
Entity processes.
Now, we focus on the first entity.
The first entity in our framework.
Processes.
A process refers to software-related activities.
These activities include requirements, engineering, detailed design, coding, integration, testing,
and maintenance.
Yes.
Maintenance.
One key characteristic of process is that they have duration.
They happen over time.
There is a clear start.
There is execution.
And there is completion.
Because processes unfold over time.
The measurement approach must capture that temporal dimension.
The slide highlights three key metrics for processes.
Duration.
How long.
Yes.
How long does the process take?
And effort.
Cost.
How much personal cost or human effort is involved?
And incident count.
Incident count.
How many errors, effects, or significant events occur during the process?
Let's break these down.
Duration measures the total time from start to completion.
For example, how many days does integration take?
Duration helps us evaluate scheduling efficiency and planning accuracy.
Effort usually refers to personal costs.
It's often measured in person with person hours or person months.
Effort tells us how many resources were consumed during the activity.
A short duration with very high effort might indicate parallel staffing.
A long duration with low effort might indicate inefficiency or delays.
Yes.
The incident count.
Incident count represents measurable events during the process.
These could be requirements, changes.
Defects.
Disforced.
Integration failures or review findings.
Incident counts could be requirements, requirement changes.
Defects discovered and failures of integration or review findings.
Incident metrics help evaluate processes.
For example, if many defects are found during formal inspection, that may indicate strong detection capability.
If many defects are found later in production, that may indicate weaknesses in earlier phase.
Notice how these metrics are interconnected.
Duration and effort combine to describe costs.
Incident counts help us evaluate effectiveness and quality control within the process.
Processes are dynamic entities.
They transform resources into products.
When measuring processes, we are not measuring structure.
We are measuring performance over time.
So, when defining a goal related to process improvements, we must ask, do we want to reduce duration?
Do we want to optimize efforts?
Do we want to decrease late stage incidents?
Clear goals lead to meaningful process metrics.
Measuring process effectiveness.
Now, we move deeper into process analysis with measuring process effectiveness.
When we talk about effectiveness, we are asking a simple,
but powerful question.
Are we getting good results compared to what we invest?
On the left side, we see the inputs, typically expressed as total costs or efforts.
And on the right side, we see the outputs, often expressed as measurable results,
such as errors per kilo or total number of detected defects.
Between them, we evaluate an efficiency index.
Look at two important derivative metrics.
First, cost per error equals to total cost division number of errors.
Cost per error equals to total cost division number of errors.
This metric tells us how much we are spending to detect or correct each defect.
If cost per error is very high, the process may be inefficient.
If it is low, the process may be cost-free.
If it is low, the process may be cost-effective.
But we must also consider quality.
Second, inspection efficiency is equal to effort expanded division clock reuse.
And this measure relates effort to the size of the product inspected.
It gives us insight into productivity
during inspection activities.
For example, how many person-hours are needed to review 1,000 lines of code.
Yes, how many person-hours are needed to review 1,000 lines of code.
These metrics combine process and product measurements.
Effort is a process attribute.
Clock is a product attribute.
Errors are incident counts.
When we combine them, we obtain indirect measures that help managers make decisions.
Managers often use these internal process statistics to judge broader external attributes,
like stability, controllability, and quality.
For instance, if inspection efficiency improves while error detection remains strong,
that may indicate process improvements.
However, effectiveness is not just about minimizing costs.
A process that is cheap but fails to detect defects early,
it may lead to much higher downstream costs.
So, effectiveness always involves balance.
The key idea here is comparison between inputs.
And outputs.
What goes into the process?
And what comes out of the process?
And what is the relationship between them?
That relationship defines process effectiveness.
Now we turn to the second measured entity in our framework.
It's products.
A product is defined as
many artifacts or documents resulting from a process activity.
This is very important.
When we say products,
we are not only talking about the final software.
We are not only talking about the final software delivered to customers.
We are talking about
every artifact created during development.
For example,
requirements documents,
design diagrams,
source code,
they are written in the slide,
documentation,
and test data.
All of these are products.
This means measurement does not apply only
to the final executable system.
It applies at every stage of the lifecycle.
Requirements can be measured.
Designs can be measured.
Even test data and documentation can be measured.
Let's consider some examples.
For requirements,
we must or we might measure size,
clarity,
redundancy,
or number of requirement changes.
For designs,
we could measure modularity,
coupling,
cohesion,
or structural complexity.
For source code,
we often measure lines of code,
cinematic complexity,
structuredness,
or reuse level.
For documentation,
we might examine length,
completeness,
readability,
or consistency.
For test data,
we might measure coverage,
size,
or fault detection capability.
The key insight here is that
software development is like a production line.
Each stage produces artifacts
that influence later stages.
If requirements are ambitious,
design quality may suffer.
If design structure is weak,
code reliability may decrease.
So,
product measurement gives us visibility
into quality only in the lifecycle.
Instead of waiting
until deployments to detect problems,
we analyze intermediate artifacts.
Another important point is the difference
between internal and external product attributes.
Internal attributes describe structure,
like size or complexity.
External attributes describe behavior,
like reliability or usability.
Most early stage product measurements
focus on internal attributes.
Later,
when the system runs in its environments,
we evaluate external attributes.
In summary,
products exist throughout the lifecycle.
A measurement must follow them
at every stage,
not only at delivery.
Yes.
Now we come to a very important idea
in software measurements.
The structural,
the structural assumption.
The structural assumption says that
good internal structure
leads to good external quality.
On the left side,
we see internal structure.
Things like modularity or low coupling
and high cohesion.
These are internal product attributes.
They describe
how the system is organized.
How the system is organized internally.
They describe
how the system is organized internally.
We can measure them without running the software.
We can inspect diagrams.
We can analyze code.
On the right side,
we see external quality.
They are internal and external attributes,
such as maintainability,
reliability,
or user satisfaction.
These depend on behavioral in real use.
They reflect how the system performs
in its environments.
Between these two sides,
there is a bridge.
And that bridge represents
If the internal structure is strong, then external quality will also be strong.
So, if the internal structure is strong, that means the external quality will also be strong.
This idea has been widely accepted in software engineering.
Frederick Brooks, in his book, My Tickle Month, emphasizes that good top-down design makes flaws more visible.
Structural design methods.
Objects.
Object-oriented design and modern architectural principles are all built on this belief.
If we give an example, high cohesion suggests models are focused and understandable.
Low coupling suggests changes in one model will not heavily affect others.
Clear structure suggests easier.
testing and modification. All of these internal properties are expected to
improve external outcomes like maintainability and reliability.
However, this is still an assumption. It's intuitive but it must be
validated. Just because a system works well-structured does not automatically
guarantee high reliability or user satisfaction. This is where measurement
becomes critical. Measurement allows us to test whether this bridge is strong. We
can collect data on internal attributes and compare them
with external outcomes. Over time we can determine whether strong structure
truly correlates with high quality. So the key message here is this. We assume
good structure leads to good quality. But only careful measurement can confirm
that relationship.
Now we have Slide 10. The danger of a single quality metric. Here we examine an
important warning, danger of single quality metric. In many organizations
there is a temptation to reduce quality to one number. A single index. A single
score.
Sometimes simple, that quickly reads and compares.
But this approach is risky.
The slide represents the GNP analogy.
It means Gross National Product is a composite number that summarizes the economic output of a country.
However, GNP is not the same as happiness.
A country can have high economic output while still having social problems, inequality or low life satisfaction.
Similarly, in software engineering, code complexity is not equal to quality.
Complexity is an internal attribute.
It measures structural characteristics of code.
But quality is multidimensional.
It includes reliability, maintainability, usability, performance and more.
When we create a single quality index, we combine different internal attributes into one composite number.
But,
this creates several problems.
The weights assigned to each component may be arbitrary.
Important dimensions may be ignored.
A high overall score may hide weaknesses in specific areas.
For example, a simple may have low complexity but poor documentation.
Or,
a small may have strong modularity but low usability.
A single metric can hide these differences.
The image on the left side illustrates this idea.
There is an internal rule filter rejecting a model simply because it contains many go-to statements.
Counting go-tos
might be used as a crude structural indicator.
But,
eliminating a model based only on that rule does not guarantee better quality.
This highlights an important principle.
Internal metrics are useful.
But,
they are only partial indicators.
Composite measures must be validated carefully.
We must ask,
do the components fully represent what we mean by quality?
Are the weights justified?
Does the composite measure correlate with external attributes like reliability and user satisfaction?
Quality is multidimensional.
Reducing it to one number
can oversimplify reality.
So, the key measure here is caution.
Measurements should clarify reality but
not hide it behind a single convenient index.
Yes.
Now,
we come to the third measure entity in our framework.
Resources.
Resources are the inputs required for software production.
Without resources,
no process can operate and no product can be created.
In this slide,
resources are grouped into three main categories.
Personal,
Tools,
and Environments.
Now, let's begin with Personal.
Personal indicates developers,
testers or designers,
managers,
teams.
When measuring personal,
we often focus on attributes such as
experience,
for example,
number of years in software development,
or intelligence,
intelligence or skill level,
team size,
or communicates structure.
These attributes influence productivity and product quality.
For example,
a highly experienced team may produce more maintainable calls.
However,
simply increasing team size does not always increase productivity.
Measurement helps us understand these relationships.
Next, we look at Tools.
Tools include hardware and software systems used during development.
We might measure
software speed,
software license cost,
storage capacity,
and automation level.
Tool attributes affect process efficiency,
for example,
caster hardware may reduce build time.
Advanced testing tools may increase defect detection rates,
but
tools also introduce
cost,
so their benefits must justify their investments.
Finally, we consider the Environments.
Environments includes
physical
and organizational conditions,
such as
office space,
temperature,
lighting,
and workplace ergonomics.
These may seem secondary,
but they influence human performance.
A pure environment can reduce concentration and productivity.
Measurements make
these factors visible.
The slide emphasizes that resources are measured in three main dimensions.
Magnitude
how many,
for instance,
number of developers,
cost,
how much,
for instance,
to licensing expenses,
and quality,
what level of skill or capability.
An important concept here is Productivity.
Productivity often combines product outputs with resource efforts.
For example,
output efforts
disconnects resources with processes and products.
So when analyzing project performance,
we must ask
are resource levels
appropriate
or it is in good level?
Is the skill level sufficient?
Are tools improving efficiency?
Is the environment supporting performance?
These are the questions we must ask
when analyzing project performance.
Measurement of resources allows managers to control inputs
in order to improve outputs.
With these slides,
we now complete the three entity model,
processes,
products,
and resources.
The full geometry also bear measurements.
We have completed here.
So let's take a look at what the next slide is.
The Productivity Equation.
Yes.
Now we examine one of the most fundamental concepts
in resource management.
The Productivity Equation.
The equation is simple.
Productivity equals to
amount of outputs,
division,
efforts,
inputs.
At first glance,
this looks straightforward.
If we produce more outputs
with less efforts,
productivity increases.
If effort increases
without increasing outputs,
productivity decreases.
But in software engineering,
this equation is more complex than it appears.
In manufacturing,
productivity is often linear.
A factory produces identical items repeatedly.
If you add more workers or fesser machines,
output increases in a predictable way.
This is replication.
The relationship between input and output is relatively stable.
Software development,
uh,
is different.
It's not replication.
It's design and creation.
Each system,
each future,
each model can be unique.
The relationship between effort and output is non-linear.
For example,
adding more developers does not always increase output proportionally.
Sometimes,
communication overheat increases.
Coordination becomes harder.
Productivity per person may decrease.
This is known in project management
as diminishing returns in team scaling.
Another important issue is defining output.
What counts as output in software?
Linus quotes
or
functionality delivered
or story points completed,
number of models implemented.
Different definitions of output lead to different productivity values.
Effort input is usually measured in person hours or person months.
But even effort measurements can vary depending on
whether we include rework,
testing,
or documentation.
This slide also highlights an important insight.
A productive worker
in one process
may become less productive if the process changes.
What does that mean?
This means
productivity depends
on,
depends not only on personal,
but also on process,
structure,
and tool support.
So while the productivity equation
works simply mathematically,
its interpretation in software engineering
requires careful definition
of both output and effort.
Productivity is not just about
working harder.
It's about organizing processes and resources effectively
to produce meaningful outputs.
Now we address a practical challenge in software measurements
using
surrogates for prediction.
This is a dilemma in software engineering.
Many of the attributes we care about
most,
such as cost,
reliability,
and user satisfaction,
are external attributes.
They depend on
real-world usage.
They often appear
late in the development lifecycle.
And they are difficult to measure early.
For example,
we cannot fully measure system reliability,
reliability before deployments.
We cannot precisely measure
long-term maintenance costs
before the system evolves.
But managers need estimates early.
Decisions must be made
before the final product exists.
So what is the strategy we use?
Internal attributes as surrogates.
A surrogate is a substitute indicator.
Instead of directly measuring reliability,
we measure something related to it,
such as design faults,
code defects,
structural complexity,
or inspection results.
For instance,
if we detect a high number of decision faults early,
this may predict lower future reliability.
If modularity is strong
and coupling is low,
this may suggest better maintainability.
The key idea is prediction.
Internal attributes are measurable early,
because they are structural and static.
External attributes are observable later,
because they are behavioral and dynamic.
Surrogates connect the present to the future.
However,
this approach depends on validation.
A surrogate must have a demonstrated relationship
between the external outcome.
If there is no
empirical evidence linking
internal design faults to measure failures,
then the surrogate is unreliable.
So when using surrogates,
we must ask,
does this internal metric correlate
with an external attribute we care about?
Is the relationship stable across projects?
Has it been validated?
Empirically?
Surrogates allow early estimation
or estimation of future outcomes
based on measurable internal metrics.
In summary,
surrogates help us make
informed predictions
before external results are visible.
Now we turn to an essential concept
in software measurements.
Measurement over time.
Software systems are not static.
They evolve.
New features are added.
Bugs are fixed.
Teams change.
Tools improve.
Because of this,
measurement cannot focus on a single snapshot.
We must absorb trends.
The graph on the slide shows
attribute values across multiple versions.
Version 1, version 2, and version 3.
The horizontal axis represents time.
The vertical axis represents
the value of an attribute.
Let's interpret the example trends.
The orange line on the slide you can see,
this line represents design decay.
The orange line represents the design decay.
Over time, the value increases.
This may indicate
growing structural complexity
or decreasing modularity.
Even if the system is functional,
internal structure might be
deteriorating.
The blue line represents reliability growth.
Reliability may improve gradually
as defects are fixed
and testing improves.
This is a positive trend.
The dashed line represents
personal turnover.
This line fluctuates.
It shows that human resources,
the human resource changes,
the human resource changes
can vary significantly over time,
influencing both processes and products.
The key message here is that
the trends
the direction and rate of change
is often more important
than the current value.
A system with moderate complexity
but repeatedly increasing design decay
is more concerning
than a system with slightly higher
but stable complexity.
Similarly,
a temporary drop in reliability
may be less critical
than a continuous downward trend.
Measurement over time allows us to
detect design decay early,
observe improvements in reliability,
identify instability in resources,
evaluate process changes.
For example,
if we introduce a new inspection process,
we should track defects
density over multiple versions
to see if the change is effective.
This slide reminds us
that software measurement is dynamic.
We are not just measuring attributes.
We are tracing.
We are tracking evolution.
In practice,
effective management depends on
measuring,
understanding trends,
not just isolated numbers.
And I think this is our last slide.
Now we arrive at the full picture,
the complete goal-based framework.
At this point,
we have discussed processes,
products and resources,
and we have distinguished
between internal attributes
and external attributes.
This slide combines everything
into one structured wheel.
On the left side,
we see the three entities,
personal,
excuse me,
processes,
products and resources.
Across the top,
we see two categories of attributes,
internal attributes
and external attributes.
Yes,
discrete and structural grids,
each entity can have both
internal and external attributes.
For example,
for processes,
internal attributes,
efforts,
cycle time,
external attributes,
adoption and efficiency.
But for products,
internal attributes,
defects,
complexity,
external attributes,
usability and satisfaction.
For resources,
internal attributes,
capacity utilization,
external attributes,
costs,
return on investment,
or ROI.
This framework shows that measurement
is multidimensional.
We are not measuring only products.
We are not measuring only
internal metrics.
We are analyzing entities across
structural and behavioral dimensions.
Now let's look at the paths
to measurements.
On the right side,
it defines a clear sequence.
It defines the goal.
What do we want to improve?
Reliability, productivity,
or maintainability?
Classification of the entity.
Are we focusing on process,
a product or resource,
and select attributes?
Are we measuring an internal
structural property or an
external behavioral outcome?
Only after these steps do we
select specific metrics.
This is the essence of a goal-based
framework.
Measurement begins with intention.
It's not random data collection.
It's structured, aligned, and purposeful.
By following this framework,
organizations can ensure that metrics
are relevant to strategic goals.
Measurements support decision-making.
Internal indicators are connected
to external outcomes.
These slides bring together
the geometry, classification,
lenses, surrogates, and time dimension
into one coherent model.
Yes.
And this completes the structure's
foundation of goal-based software measurements.
Okay, we are up this week.
Thank you for listening to me.
So let's meet next week.
Take care of yourself.
Bye.