good morning friends can you hear me can we make a technical check please if you can hear me just
write in the chat box okay if you are able to hear me please write okay in the chat box okay
okay i think we haven't finished the last week's topic yet as far as i remember we were studying
the slide number eight this is the slide number eight so we will continue from that point
just trying to what's what number eight
your article of measurement as i remember yes here yes we were at this point let's continue here
excellent
let's see this okay now everything comes together in the hierarchical of measurement power
the hierarchy of measurement power think of this table as a letter as me as we move from nominal
ordinal internal ratio and absolute to the table of measurement
two things happen at the same time our analytical power increases but the freedom of
the freedom to transform the numbers becomes more restricted at the nominal level life is easy and
any one-to-one mapping is fine because we only preserve identity fault types are different
categories nothing more but but our analysis power is minimal when we move to ordinal
we must keep the rank transformations must be monolithic transformations must be monotonic
we gain the ability to say higher or lower like complexity levels but we still cannot talk about
distances okay at the interval level we protect differences now transformations follow the
affine from em plus b because because intervals are meaningful
subtraction becomes valid start dates and temperature live here but ratios are still
forbidden because zero can move at the racial level things get serious we now preserve ratios
transformations can only multiply by a no shifting this is why execution
time
or program length let us say twice as long finally the absolute level is pure counting
no transformation at all identity only error count is exactly what it is
so every step upwards gives a stronger mathematics but demands tricker discipline about what changes
are allowed whenever you face a metric a good reflex is to ask which row of this hierarchy am i in
because that answer immediately tells you which conclusions are safe and which are dangerous okay
now let's skip slides nine now we hit uh
one of the most philosophical and maybe most important ideas meaningfulness many people think
that if a statement is true then it must automatically be meaningful but it is not correct
troops and meaningfulness are different things a statement is meaningful
if its true value says the same under all admissible transformations of the scale.
In other words, when we legally change units or representations, the conclusion must survive.
If the result flips from true to false or if the result changes from true to false,
then the statements never had solid grounds.
Let's look at the example with age.
The president is 125 years old.
Is this meaningful?
Yes, age is on a racial scale.
If we convert years into months, days or seconds, the arithmetic structure remains consistent.
The statement may be false in reality, but mathematically it's stable.
Therefore, it is meaningful.
And that leads to a beautiful conclusion.
You can have a meaningful lie, but you cannot have a meaningless truth.
Okay, this is important.
Maybe you may have a meaning lie.
Lie means not true.
But you can...
You can not have a truth without any meaning.
If a claim collapses when we change units in an allowed way,
then even if it accidentally matches reality once, it is not scientifically valid.
Okay?
So from now on, whenever someone presents a numerical conclusion, we should ask,
Would this still hold after every admissible transformation?
If it is yes, meaningful.
If no, ill-issued.
Slide number nine.
Great.
Now we start stress testing conclusions.
If we take a look at the slides.
Now, up to now, we know that stress testing is a very important part of life.
So here we learn the theory of scales and admissible transformations.
Here we use that knowledge like a filter.
Every claim must survive the test.
The complexity trap.
A semantic error is twice as complex as a semantic error.
This sounds scientific.
It never sounds precise.
But it is invalid. Why? Because complexity here is only ordinal. We can rank errors, maybe from easy to hard, but we don't know the distance between the ranks.
Since ratios are not preserves, the word twice has no foundation. It's a story created by numbers, not by scale.
Maybe it's better to... The speed comparison. Program A is faster than program B. This one is valid.
It's valid.
We are making an ordering statement. Ordinal scales are perfectly capable of supporting rank comparisons.
No matter how we re-label or transform the ranking, if A was above B, it will remain above B.
The twice as fast claim.
Program A is faster than program B. It's a story created by numbers, maybe from easy to hard, but we don't know the distance between the ranks.
Maybe it's better to compare alto and alto every attack.
The speed comparison. Program C is more than twice as fast as program C.
Now things become conditional. If speed is measured only as a ranking, meaning less.
If speed is measured with real-time units like seconds, ratios scale valid.
So the statement is not automatically real.
automatically wrong it depends on the measurement system behind it this slide teaches a very
practical survival survival rule whenever you hear twice half three times your brain should
immediately ask do we truly have a racial scale if not danger as the next slide slides number
11 this is where many real world mistakes happen
yes welcome to statistical safety guides the table answers a practical question
which statistics are legal for which states because if the scale does not support the math
the result becomes
nonsense even if it looks professional start with a nominal data we only know
categories no order no distance therefore the only safe statistic is the mode
the most frequent class medium impossible mean meaningless standard deviation
pure fantasy move to ordinal now we have order so we can talk about
position in a ranking that makes medium acceptable because it depends on who is in the middle
not on distances mode is still fine but the mean is forbidden why because averaging assumes equals
or something like that the general idea was that having this central order means
some sort of change would be кажд earther stands at a hundred points and are a failure
thank you for the randomness in this class
though the showed this evidence is beyond comparison let's move on to standard deviation
this practice turns perso 우와
with no sizable change in place
no stakeholders
of a lie level life becomes easier differences are meaningful so mean and standard deviation
now makes sense but geometrics mean still requires ratios so not yet finally ratio and absolute
scales allow almost everything because we have a true zero multiplication and division are
legitimate all common statistics become safe the warning at the bottom is famous for a reason
taking the mean of ordinary data like server ratings
can produce
mathematical gibberish mathematical gibberish it may look precise it may give decimals but
precision is artificial so before computing any statistics always ask
does my scale authorize this operation yes the next slide is this slide delivers
a punch the average can lie to you when the scale is ordinary let's let's walk through the ordinal
mean paradox in mapping a we use a normal one to five ranking system y has ranks three three three
The mean is, in this case, 3.4, yes.
System X has ranks 2, 2, 2, 5, 5.
The mean is calculated as 3.2.
So the conclusion seems clear.
Y is higher.
Now we apply a perfectly legal operation for ordinal data.
A monolithic transformation.
Order must stay the same, but magnitudes can change.
We simply turn the highest label, 5, into 10.
Nothing illegal happens.
After transformation, system Y, still 3, 3, 3, 4, 4.
The mean is...
Calculated as 3.4.
System X becomes 2, 2, 2, 10, 10.
In this case, the mean is increased as 5.2.
Suddenly, X is higher.
Same reality, same ordering, only the labels changed.
If a conclusion flips under...
And admissible transformation, we already know the verdict.
It is meaningless.
That's why...
Competing the mean for ordinal data is dangerous.
The average pretentious distances exist, but the scale never guaranteed them.
What survives the transformation?
Of course, the median.
The median.
In both...
In both mapping, the median still tells us why it is higher.
It depends only on order, and order is preserved.
So, the rule becomes very, very practical.
If your data is ordinal, trust the median.
Be suspicious of the mean.
Nice.
This slide prevents a common misunderstanding.
After hearing that ordinal averages are problematic,
some people jump to a dangerous conclusion.
Then subjective ratings are useless.
No, absolutely not.
Here we see the value of subjective measurements.
Ratings run from one...
Equals 15.
One.
2.5 equals clear. 2.5 equals means confusing. Yes, this is ordinal. Yes, computing a mean can be mathematically questionable, but look at the distribution.
Sure. Performance, database, and other areas clustered towards the lower values. Most responses are around clear or slightly unclear, but the interface shows something very different.
Many ratings gather near 4 and 5. You do not need perfect arithmetic to notice the signal.
There is a wizard.
It is a visible problem cluster, so even when the scale limits which formulas are legal, the data can still guide decisions, frequencies, mediums, shapes, or distributions.
These remain powerful.
The key message is substantial but important.
Imprecise measurement does not mean useless measurement.
It means we must choose the correct interpretation tools.
Instead of asking what is the average confusing, we should ask where do responses accumulate.
That question stays faithful to the ordinal nature of the data.
Now we move into situations where one number is not enough.
Many real problems involve multidimensional attributes.
Think about choosing between a car, a train, or a plane.
What matters?
Time, cost, comfort, risk, flexibility?
More than one dimension?
Because of this simple ranking,
it becomes tricky.
A is superior to B only if A is better on all relevant counts.
For example, time A is smaller than time B and cost E is smaller than cost B.
Only then can we confidently see that A is superior to B.
Only if A is better on all relevant counts.
Only then can we confidently see that A is better on all relevant counts.
Eventually say A dominates B. But what if A is faster and B is cheaper?
Now we face a trade-off. Neither option is strictly better, they become uncomparable.
That is exactly what the diagram shows. Some errors exist where one option clearly dominates another.
But between certain choices, like train versus plane, there may be no error, which wins on a different dimension.
This breaks a habit many people have, forcing everything into a single ranking.
In multidimensional measurement, a total order may simply not exist.
So,
Instead of asking which one is best, we often must ask better in which aspect.
The moment multiple attributes are involved, comparisons become more careful, more conditional and more honest.
And the last slide is slide number 15.
This wraps the entire journey.
The topic was never just numbers.
It was about the integrity of the metric, whether conclusions truly respect reality.
The context is king.
Before doing any math, we must ask what kind of attributes we are measuring.
determined by how the property behaves in the real world, not by the symbols we write
down.
Two metrics may both use numbers, but one might only label categories while the other
supports division.
Respect the Hierarchy Each level of measurement authorizes certain
operations and forbids others.
Problems begin when we try to push ratio mathematics onto ordinal rankings.
Multiplication averages twice as much.
They create an illusion of precision that the scale never promised.
Seek meaningfulness.
A result is soon.
The result is soon.
There is trustworthiness only if it remains true after every admissible transformation.
Change the units.
Label the values.
If the conclusion survives, it has substance.
If it flips, it is fragile from the start This leads to the final mindset shift.
The real question is not what number did we compute?
The real question is what statements are we allowed to make with it?
If we follow that discipline, metrics become powerful tools.
If we ignore it, they become elegant nonsense.
Okay, we have finished the last week's slides.
So this is, as I remember, this is the fourth week.
We have finished the first three weeks' topics.
So let me sign it.
We have finished the third week.
Yes, let me give me some time, please.
Yes, the third week, software metrics.
Okay.
Otherwise, I'm forgetting which point have we finished or not.
And after that, we will continue.
We will go through the week four.
Yes, yes, week three.
Okay, now we are in week four now.
So let me stop the sharing.
And...
Upload the new document here.
Software metric week four.
It will take a few seconds.
After that, we can continue.
But we didn't make a technical check.
I hope to see me and hear me clearly.
Otherwise, it's a problem.
Anyway, I'm sharing all the documents we are studying.
To the system, please check it.
And recommend you to read the slides at the corresponding main book.
Also, share it.
Upload at the main book.
Week by week, I have divided the main book into some sections.
And every week, I'm studying, teaching the corresponding section.
And every section...
Are being uploaded to the system.
So you can understand easily which section we are studying now.
You can understand that.
And recommend not to collect all these sections to the week of the examinations.
Because it will be problem for you.
Step by step, if you study, there is no any reason in order not to be succeed.
So, please at least read twice before the week.
Before the courses.
Every week, it will help you, greatly help you.
To be prepared for the examinations.
Okay.
Now, the fallacy of a single numbering software engineering.
Now, let's start with an important idea.
The fallacy of a single number in software engineering.
Very often in software projects, we try to reduce complex concepts.
Like quality, complexity, or effort into just one number.
We feel comfortable when we see a single value.
It looks clear, objective, and easy to compare.
But this can be misleading.
When we say a system has...
Sorry.
When...
Yes.
If we say a system has high quality or low complexity.
What do we really mean?
Quality can include reliability, usability.
Performance, maintainability, and many other attributes.
Complexity can depend on structure, dependencies, control flow, and even human understanding.
Efforts may involve the time, cost, experience level, and team coordination.
So, reducing all of this into one number can destroy important information.
The key idea here is moving from naive ranking to regions.
Multi-dimensional measurements.
Naive ranking means we simply order systems from best to worst.
Based on one value.
But real measurements should preserve relationships between entities.
Measurement is not just assigning numbers.
It's about representing reality in a structured way.
If two systems are different in different dimensions.
For example, one is faster but more expensive.
How can a single number truly represent that trade-off?
In many cases, it's not.
It cannot.
That's why multi-dimensional measurements using vectors or multiple attributes is often more accurate and more honest.
So, as we continue.
Keep these questions in mind.
When we measure something in software engineering.
Are we really capturing its structure?
Or are we oversimplifying it into a single convenient number?
Okay.
You can think of this.
But how can I stretch?
Okay.
Slide number two.
Let's think about the transport paradox.
And why the idea of better is often subjective.
Imagine we want to travel between two cities.
We want to rank the options from best to worst.
At first, this seems easy.
We collect data.
Journey time.
And costs per mile.
The numbers look clear.
Car takes three hours.
And costs 1.5 per mile.
Let's say that.
Train takes five hours.
And costs two.
Totally.
Yes.
Plane takes 3.5.
3.5.
Hour.
Hours.
But costs 3.5.
Coach is seven hours.
And four dollars.
Let me repeat again.
Car takes three hours.
And costs 1.5 dollars.
Train.
Five hours.
And two dollars.
Playing.
3.5 hours.
And 3.5 dollars.
And the coach is seven hours.
And four dollars.
Now, look at the car.
It is faster and cheaper.
Than the train.
It's also better than the coach.
In both dimensions.
So, we can clearly say.
Car is superior to those options.
No problem here.
When we compare train and plane.
Something interesting happens.
Yes.
Train is cheaper.
But slower.
Plane is faster.
But more expensive.
So, which one is better?
It depends on what we value more.
Time or money.
If speed is more important.
Plane looks better.
If cost matters more.
Train looks better.
There is no objective answer.
Without adding extra information.
About priorities.
This is the key idea.
When we have two attributes.
And one option is better in one dimension.
But worse in another.
The options become incomparable.
We no longer have a simple ranking.
Instead.
We have what measurement theory calls.
A partial order.
Strict ranking becomes impossible.
Unless we introduce subjective weighting.
And the moment we assign.
The weights.
We are no longer purely measuring.
We are making a decision.
Based on preferences.
This example shows.
Why a single number often fails.
Reality is multidimensional.
If we try to force.
Everything into one scale.
Without justification.
We lose important structure.
So the question becomes.
We say.
One software system is better.
Than another.
Are we comparing.
All relevant dimensions.
Or.
Are we ignoring trade-offs.
Okay.
Think of this.
Please.
Let's move.
To a more formal argument.
The mathematical proof.
Of.
Impossibility.
The mathematical proof.
Of.
Impossibility.
Assume we try to define.
A single real number.
Let's call it.
M.
That represents quality.
According to measurement theory.
If.
Such a measure exists.
It must map each entity.
For example.
Plane and train.
Into a set of real numbers.
Are.
While preserving the.
In particular.
Relationships.
This requirement is known.
As the representation.
Condition.
Representation.
So we assume.
That such a number.
Exists.
Then one of three things.
Must be true.
Either.
M.
Plane.
Smaller than.
M.
Train.
Or.
M.
Plane.
Greater than.
M.
Train.
Or.
M.
Plane.
Is equal to.
M.
Train.
There are no other possibilities.
In real numbers.
Let's examine.
Each case.
If.
M.
Plane.
Is smaller than.
M.
Train.
This means.
That.
Contradicts.
The fact.
That.
Plane.
Is.
Faster.
If.
M.
Plane.
Is.
Greater than.
M.
Train.
This means.
Plane.
Is.
Better than.
Train.
But.
That.
Contradicts.
The fact.
That.
Train.
Is.
Cheaper.
If.
Is.
Bigger.
Than.
Train.
Time.
And.
Cost.
Per.
Mile.
All three possibilities.
Lead.
To.
Contradiction.
Why.
Does.
Happen.
Because.
This.
Is.
The.
Relationship.
Between.
Plane.
And.
Train.
Is.
A.
Partial.
Order.
Not.
way but here some pairs are incomparable one option is better in one dimension and worse
in another i think the camera the light of the camera is not good enough maybe
let me try to turn off the lights
is this better no okay okay i cannot do anything unfortunately maybe it's better to
close the curtain is this better i don't know let me change again it's not it doesn't work
and that's that's all i can do unfortunately okay let's continue since uh real numbers
always
impose a strict total ordering they cannot correctly represent partial
orders without losing information therefore no single real number can
represent represent quality in this case without destroying the structure of the
data this is the core mathematical insight when entities are genuinely
incomparable a single scalar value cannot satisfy the representation
condition and this idea applies directly to software engineering if quality
complexity or efforts are multi-dimensional
then forcing them into one real number is not just simplistic it is
mathematically incorrect it's not correct applying partial orders to code
complexity we often use cinematic complexity as a single number to
represent how complex a program is
we often use cinematic complexity as a single number to represent how complex a program is
the higher the number the more complex the program is supposed to be it sounds
logical it feels objective but here we meet what we can call the
cinematic fantasy look at the three structures X is a sequence Y is
conditional that is a loop
loop the cinematic complexity values are X is equal to 3 Y is 2 and that is 2
according to the number X is more complex than that because 3 is greater
greater than 2 so mathematically the ranking seems clear but
Now, think like an engineer. Many developers would discuss that a loop is harder to understand and maintain than a simple sequence of conditionals.
A loop introduces iteration, possible infinite behavior, boundary conditions and more cognitive load.
So, we have a situation similar to the transport example. The numeric ranking tells one story. Engineering intuition tells another story.
Why does this happen? Because complexity is multidimensional.
Cinematic complexity measures the number of linearly independent paths.
It does not measure cognitive difficulties.
Nesting depth, data dependencies or maintainability directly.
So, when we compare a sequence and a loop, we are not comparing simple objects.
We are comparing structures with different characteristics, just like train and plane.
They may be incomparable in some dimensions.
This means the relation, more complex than, may not be a strict Weib order.
And if it is not, then mapping it to a single real number, like psychologic complexity, cannot fully preserve the structure.
The verdict is important.
Forcing different code structures into a single order of scale creates a false hierarchy.
It gives us clarity, but possibly at the cost of truth.
The real question is, are we measuring complexity or are we only measuring one aspect of it and pretending it presents the whole?
So, if a single real number does not work, what is the solution?
The answer is vector representation.
Instead of mapping entities into the set of real numbers R, we map them into R by R.
Or more generally into an array of numbers.
And this is the solution.
This means we represent each entity using multiple values, not just one.
In the transport example, we defined m transport equals time and cost.
So, instead of seeing car has quality 7.2,
m car equals to 3 and 1.5.
Yes.
Now we preserve both dimensions.
In this case, we do not lose both information.
And most importantly, we preserve the empirical relationships.
If one option is better in both time and cost,
then superiority is visible in the pair comparison.
This is the key idea.
When data is multidimensional, the representation must also be multidimensional.
And this is not just a theoretical idea.
It is exactly the approach taken by idealists.
The approach taken by ISO IEC 25010 for software quality.
This standard does not define quality as a single number.
Instead, it defines software quality as a set of distinct sub-attributes,
such as functional suitability, performance comparability,
usability, reliability, security, maintainability, and portability.
In other words, software quality is treated as a vector,
a structured set of attributes.
We must stop flattening multidimensional data into a single scalar value.
When we do that, we are simply too much.
And risk misrepresentation.
So, instead of asking what is the quality number,
a better question is what are the relevant dimensions and how do they interact?
The rules of derivative measurements.
Now, let's talk about the rules of derivative measurements.
The camera is very bad.
The lighting.
Yes, it's not good.
Okay.
So far, we discussed the direct measurement and vector representation.
But in practice, we often combine measures to create a new one.
This is called a derivative measure.
A classic example is density.
We define density as
density d is equal to mass over volume, m over v.
Here, mass and volume are direct measures.
Density is derived from them.
But there is an important condition.
The relationship must remain valid under rescaling.
What does rescaling mean?
It means changing the units.
For example, we can measure mass in grams or kilograms.
We can measure volume in liters or cubic meters.
These are different units.
But they represent the same physical reality.
A valid derivative measure must behave consistently when units change.
If we multiply mass by a constant factor,
because we change units,
the density value should transform in a predictable and admissible way.
It should not suddenly destroy the relationship.
So, the rule is this.
A derivative measure is meaningful only if admissible transformations of the components lead to admissible transformations.
If mass is rescaled properly and volume is rescaled properly,
then density must also rescale correctly.
If that does not happen,
the derived formula is not meaningful from a measurement theory perspective.
Now think about software engineering.
When we define metrics like productivity equals to line of code over effort.
The productivity is equal lines of code over effort.
Or defect density equals to defects over kilo.
We are also creating derived measures.
We must check,
we must control
whether changing units,
for example,
from lines to thousands of lines,
produces valid transformations.
If the scale types of the components are weak,
the derivative measure cannot be stronger than them.
For example,
if one component is only ordinal,
the final measure cannot magically
become a gracious scale.
So, the key idea here is discipline.
Combining numbers is easy.
Creating a meaningful derivative measure is much harder.
Whenever we define a new metric,
we should ask,
does it remain valid under rescaling?
Does it preserve the structure of the old one?
The structure of the original attributes?
Yes, the next slide is slide number seven.
The weakest link rule of scale types.
Now let's focus on an important principle
in measurement theory.
The weakest line,
the weakest link.
So, rule of scale types.
When we create a derivative measure,
its scale type cannot be stronger
than the weakest,
than the weakest components
used to calculate it.
This is a very strict rule.
Remember the hierarchy of scale types.
At the bottom,
we have nominal scales.
It's simple categories.
Then ordinal rankings
without equal intervals.
Then interval,
meaningful differences,
but no true zero.
Then ratio,
meaningful differences
and meaningful ratios.
At the top,
absolute.
Simple counts like counting box.
This hierarchy matters
when we combine measures,
the result is limited
by the weakest scale involved.
Let's look at the example on the slide.
Testing efficiency
defined as
T equals to D over E.
Here,
can I,
let me,
here,
yes.
Here,
D is the number of detects.
That is an absolute scale measure.
We are counting.
E is
efforts,
usually measured in person
months.
That is a ratio scale.
Absolute is stronger than ratio.
So we can divide D by E.
The result in measure T
remains
on a ratio scale.
That's important because
ratio scales allow meaningful statements
like double.
We can meaningfully say
testing efficiency doubles
because there is a true zero
and proportional
comparisons are valid.
But imagine
a different case.
If one component
were only ordinal,
then the entire derivative measure
would drop to ordinal at best.
Even if other components
were ratio scale,
the weakest one controls the results.
That is why it's called
the weakest link rule.
This rule protects us
from making invalid claims.
If a metric includes subjective rankings
or categorical values,
we cannot suddenly claim
strong mathematical properties
for the final number.
So,
before trusting any complex metric,
we should ask,
what are the scale types
of its components?
And which one is the weakest?
Yes.
Now we have a case study,
the Wathstone-Felix model.
Now let's examine
a concrete example
of the Felix model,
the Wathstone-Felix model.
The equation is,
as you see,
here on the slide,
E is equal to 5.2
times S to the power of 0.91.
Here E represents efforts.
E is efforts,
usually measured in person months.
And S represents software size,
typically measured in lines of code.
So,
E represents efforts.
It is measured
in person months.
S represents
the size of the software
and it is
the line of the code.
It can be measured
in lines of the code.
At first gallons,
this looks like a standard prediction model.
It tells us that efforts
grow as a power function of size.
But,
but a serious criticism
was raised by
de Milo and Lipton.
They argued or discussed
that the equation is meaningless
because the constants change.
If,
if we switch units,
for example,
from lines of code to clock,
their argument was
if constants depend
on the unit choice,
then the equation cannot be meaningful.
This sounds convicting,
but the key point here is
understanding the difference between
narrow and wide sense meaningfulness.
In the wide sense,
the equation remains meaningful
because both size and effort
are ratio scale measures.
Ratio scales
allow multiplicative transformations.
If we change units,
for example,
from log to clock,
we apply a constant scaling factor.
The relationship still preserves
the ratio properties.
So,
even if the numerical constant
in the formula change,
the underlying scale type
remains ratio.
The structure of the relationship
is preserved.
That means the question is meaningful
from a measurement theory perspective.
However,
and this is important also,
meaningfulness does not mean correctness.
A model can be mathematically meaningful,
but still empirically,
yes,
it is inaccurate.
A model,
yes,
may be mathematically meaningful,
but still inaccurate.
So,
the real conclusion is
Watson-Felix model is meaningful
in the wide sense
because it preserves ratio scale properties.
The mathematics is consistent
with measurement theory,
but whether the model predicts
effort accurately in practice
is a separate empirical question.
This case study teaches us something powerful.
Before rejecting a model,
we must check whether
the criticism is about scale theory
or about empirical validity.
These are two different issues.
Yes,
the trap of mixed scales
halstits physics.
Now,
let's look
at a very important warning.
The trap of mixed scales
illustrated by
Halstits physics.
Halstits proposed a theory
where software effort is defined as
E is equal to
V over L.
Here,
V is program volume
and is program level.
According to Halstits,
this equation measures
the mental efforts required
to implement a program.
At first glance,
it looks similar to the density example
we saw before.
It's a simple division.
It feels mathematically clean.
But now,
we must examine the scale types carefully.
Volume V is measured
on a ratio scale,
but
it's based on
counts of operators
and operands.
It has a true zero
and allows proportional comparisons.
Program level L, however,
is only on an ordinal scale,
which represents a ranking
or an estimated level,
not a true ratio measure.
And here is the
fatal flaw.
According
to the weakest link rule,
a derivative measure
cannot be stronger than
its weakest components.
Since L is ordinal,
the result E
cannot be ratio scale.
But Halstits claims
that
E measures
mental
discriminations
which would require
a ratio scale.
That would mean
we could
meaningfully say
one program requires twice
as much mental effort
as another.
This is mathematically impossible.
You cannot derive
a ratio scale measure
from an ordinal input.
The scale type collapses.
The structure does not support
ratio level interpretation.
So the problem here is
mixing incompatible scale types.
The mathematical looks correct,
but the measurement theory
is violated.
This example teaches us
something critical.
When designing software matrix,
we must not only check the formula,
we must check the scale types
of every component.
Otherwise we may
produce numbers
that look scientific but
are theoretically meaningless.
They will not have any meaning.
So here the key lesson is
combining numbers
is easy.
Combining scales correctly
is much harder.
The poison pill
in dimensional analysis.
Now let's examine
what we can call
the poison pill
in dimensional analysis.
Now consider
this effort model.
E is equal to
2.7V
plus 121.
W plus 26X plus 12Y
plus 22Z minus 497.
Here we might represent
number of instructions.
X and Y represent
internal and external documents.
Z represents program size.
And W is subjective complex
rating.
At first glance,
this equation looks detailed
and sophisticated.
Many variables, weighted coefficients,
even a constant term.
It feels scientific.
But there is a hidden problem.
The variable W is only
an ordinal scale measure.
It represents a ranking
or subjective rating
of complexity.
It does not have
equal intervals
and it does not have
a true zero.
This is the poison pill.
Because omega is ordinal,
the entire result E
collapses to ordinal scale.
According to the weakest link rule,
a derivative measure
cannot be stronger
than its weakest components.
It does not matter
what Y, X, Y and Z
might be ratio scale.
The presence of one ordinal input forces
the final measure
down to ordinal.
Yet the authors claim that
it represents effort
in personal months.
Which is a ratio scale quantity
that claim cannot be justified.
At best, this formula provides
a ranking of efforts.
It might tell us that
one project is likely to require
more effort than another.
But it cannot meaningfully tell us
that the project requires
twice as many persons
months as another.
So this example teaches
a very practical lesson.
Even one improperly scaled variable
can invalidate the scale type
of an entire model.
Before trusting any complex equation,
we must carefully examine
every input variable.
One subjective ordinal component
can quietly destroy
ratio level in the model.
And that is why
dimensional analysis in measurement theory
is not just mathematics.
It is protection against false precision.
Now let's bring everything together
with a checklist for
Regius measurements.
If we want to avoid
the fallacy of a single number
the trap of
a single number
makes it scales
and the poison-peel problem
as we have discussed
earlier now
we need a disciplined approach.
First, identify sub-attributes.
We should not measure
quality directly.
Quality is not just
primitive attribute.
Instead, we identify its
components like reliability,
like performance,
like usability,
like maintainability
and measure them separately.
Think in terms of vectors
but not scalars.
Second, check for incomparability.
Ask yourself,
are you forcing a strict order
onto something that is
actually a partial order?
Just like train versus plane.
Some entities may be better
in one dimension
and worse in another.
If so, a single ranking
may distort reality.
Third, verify scale preservation.
For every input variable,
determine its scale type.
Nominal, ordinal,
interval ratio
or absolutes.
This is not optional.
It defines what
mathematical operations
are meaningful.
Fourth, apply the weakest
link test.
After combining measures,
check the weakest input scale.
The result cannot be
stronger than that.
If one component is ordinal,
the final measure cannot
legitimately claim
ratio level meaning.
Finally, perform
wide sense validation.
Does this formula behave
correctly under rescaling?
If you change units,
for example,
from lines
to codes
to thousands of lines,
does the structure
remain valid?
A meaningful model must
survive unit transformations
without breaking its logic.
This checklist
is not just theoretical.
It is a practical filter.
Before accepting any software metric,
we can apply these five steps
and immediately detect
many common errors.
So instead of asking,
so instead of asking,
does this metric look reasonable?
A better question is,
does this metric respect
the rules of measurement theory?
Now we have the last slide.
What we have?
Nine minutes
to finish this week's course.
Yes.
Measurement is relationship preservation.
Now we arrive
at the central principle.
Measurement is relationship preservation.
Everything we discussed,
partial orders,
vector representation,
derivatives,
measurements,
weakest link rule
leads to one core idea,
the representation condition.
To measure something
means to define a mapping
from real-world entities
into a number system
in such a way that
we absorb relationships
and relationships are preserved.
That is the essence of measurement.
If in the real world
system A is better than system B
in a clearly defined way,
then our numerical representation
must reflect that.
If two systems are incomparable in reality,
our measurements must
not force an artificial ranking.
Measurement is not about
producing numbers.
It's about preserving structure.
When we assign numbers
but destroy the relationship
between entities,
we are not measuring.
We are generating noise.
That's why intuitive understanding
must precise measurements.
Before creating a metric,
we must clearly understand
the attributes we want to measure.
What are its components?
What relationships exist between entities?
Is the order strict or partial?
Are there trade-offs?
If we skip this step
and jump directly to formulas,
we risk building
an elegant but meaningless matrix.
So the final takeaway is this.
Measurement is not arithmetic.
Measurement is structure preservation.
Anything less,
is just noise.
Also, we have finished
this week's PowerPoint document.
We still have five minutes.
Maybe next time
we will spend a little bit more
to compensate these five minutes.
But I'm wondering,
still,
I cannot see any students online.
If the registration process
is continuing, it's okay.
But I need to be sure
whether any students
who take this course or not.
Otherwise,
giving this course here
does not have any meaning
unless there is no any students.
But before last week,
there were two students.
But this week,
I cannot see anybody here.
It's strange.
Okay.
Now,
I want to ask
whether the subjects
are understandable or not.
I wanted to check.
I want to give any feedback from you.
But there's no...
There's...
There is not anyone
to whom I can ask.
Okay.
Now, we have finished
the first three weeks
or maybe four weeks.
Not sure.
Yes, we have finished four weeks.
The next week will be
the week number five.
And also,
I'm sharing all my documents
necessary.
I'm uploading them to the system.
Please,
control sometimes to the system.
The main document
is available also.
The slides are available.
Maybe you cannot understand
from the slides only, but
the slides
are derived from the main documents.
Okay?
So,
I'm trying to go through the course
as parallel with slides
and the main books,
they are going parallel.
So,
the main book is better
because you can...
You have a chance to read
line by line.
Maybe
some...
There are maybe some
points that is not understandable
when you watch the video.
But,
in this case,
please refer to the main book
so you can understand easily.
Also,
if...
Whenever you have any question,
I'm here.
Just send me an email.
I will try to answer
as fast as possible.
So,
yes,
that's enough for this week.
Thank you
for listening me.
Okay.
Then,
see you next week, friends.
Take care of yourself.
Have a nice week.
Bye.